Elaine Johansen Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Elaine Johansen Papers.
undated, 1920-1994.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Johansen, Elaine.
12 linear feet.
Dr. Johansen was a Professor of Political Science at the University of Connecticut for nearly 20 years, from 1979 to 1996. In the early part of the 1980s Dr. Johansen performed an extensive study on Comparable Worth (an economic concept stressing equal pay for equal work, often applied to arguments of gender-based pay equity), including the collection of data on Comparable Worth initiatives in State legislatures. This work resulted in the publication of Comparable Worth: The Myth and the Movement in 1984. In 1990 Dr. Johansen published Political Corruption: Scope and Resources: an Annotated Bibliography. Prof. Johansen passed away in 1997 after a battle with cancer.
MSS19980368
Biography
Dr. Elaine Johansen was Professor of Political Science at the University of Connecticut for nearly 20 years, from 1979 to 1996, coming to the university after completing her Ph.D. in 1976 at the Florida State University. Her dissertation at FSU was titled, “Democratic Theory and the Political Socialization of Physicians: The Role, Mode and Significance of Professionalism in a Polity.” At the University of Connecticut, she taught courses in Public Administration and Political Science.
In the early part of the 1980s, Dr. Johansen performed an extensive study on Comparable Worth (an economic concept stressing equal pay for equal work, often applied to concepts of gender-based pay equity), including the collection of data on Comparative Worth initiatives in State legislatures. This work resulted in the publication of Comparable Worth: The Myth and the Movement in 1984. In later years Dr. Johansen took an interest in the subject of political corruption. She spent several years reviewing literature on this subject, writing a book entitled Political Corruption: Scope and Resources: an Annotated Bibliography, which was published in 1990.
Professor Johansen passed away in 1997 after a battle with cancer.
Scope and Content
Collection consists primarily of notes, manuscripts, and supporting materials for two scholarly book projects. Some correspondence is included where it relates to these projects. Dr. Johansen's personal notes were not rigorously organized, and thus some of her personal notes are interfiled in folders containing the published articles to which the notes relate.
Arrangement
Series I: Comparable Worth study (undated, 1920-1989) includes manuscripts, articles and publications on pay equity, and statistical data compiled from a study of state legislatures.
Series II: Political Corruption Materials (undated, 1987) includes manuscript versions of Johansen's book as well as copies of many of the articles discussed in the bibliography.
Series III: Teaching Materials (undated, ca. 1976-1989) includes course syllabi, lecture notes, and copies of student reports related to courses in Public Administration.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
Biographical sketch compiled from materials in the collection. Both Comparable Worth: The Myth and the Movement and Political Corruption: Scope and Resources: an Annotated Bibliography are held in the main stacks of the Homer Babbidge Library.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Organizations:
University of Connecticut--Faculty--Personal papers.
Subjects:
Political science--Study and teaching.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Manuscripts.; Publications.
Occupations:
College teachers.; Educators--Connecticut..
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Materials donated to the Dodd Center by Dr. Johansen's daughter in 1998.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Comparable Worth Materials, undated, 1920-1989
  - Campaign Finance Data—select Female Senators, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Early notes and interviews (Job Evaluation Study)
  - Conceptual notes for Comparable Worth Study
  - Notes on Job Evaluation and Comparable Worth
  - Early conceptual work on Comparable Worth (CT)
  - Student paper (overview of Comparable Worth), 1983
  - Clippings on Comparable Worth, includes a typed reply by Johansen to an article by Attorney General Smith
  - Notes and Bibliographic Materials on Comparable Worth
  - Comparable Worth--
    - contacts—action file
    - Book—correspondence, 1983-1985
    - Book—partial MS
    - Book—typescript
    - Conceptual articles and notes
    - Articles, critical
    - Newspaper clippings and scrapBook pages
  - Public Administration Times—select issues, 1982-1984
  - Comparable Worth—miscellaneous publications
  - Listing of Commissions on the Status of Women
  - Audrey Beck, Permanent Commission on the Status of Women materials
  - Audrey Beck materials and correspondence
  - Materials for conferences and talks on Comparable Worth, 1985-1987
  - ASPA, IPMA Conference notes, Carnegie Conference notes, 1983
  - IPMA Directory, 1983
  - Survey Data—professional associations, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Comparable Worth—notes on States
  - Papers and literature on Comparable Worth in the States
  - Draft of report on Comparable Worth in the States, 1984
  - Questionnaires for 50 state Comparable Worth survey
  - Contact info for 50 state survey
  - Comparable Worth—State survey responses, 1984
  - Statistical Data—Round 1 state survey
  - Data/Analysis for 50 state survey (1/3)
  - Data/Analysis for 50 state survey (2/3)
  - Data/Analysis for 50 state survey (3/3)
  - Articles and research for 50 state survey
  - Comparable Worth—State studies and legislation
  - Comparable Worth—State report from Montana
  - Comparable Worth—State legislation
  - Comparable Worth—State legislation
  - Comparable Worth—State legislation from Hawaii
  - Comparable Worth—State legislation from Virginia
  - Diffusion Literature—State politics
  - CT Job Classification Review, 1981
  - Reports on CT Job Evaluation Study
  - Status Report—CT Job Evaluation Program
  - Civil Service Reform—articles and publications (Box 3)
  - Pay Equity—Congressional hearings
  - U.S. Commission on Civil Rights—draft report, 1985
  - Notes on USCCR draft report
  - Typescript response to GAO and USCCR reports on Comparable Worth, 1985
  - Notes on Johansen's consultation of the GAO, 1984
  - Johansen's response to the Civil Rights Commission and GAO reports
  - Civil Rights Commission report—Comparable Worth Analysis and Recommendations, 1985
  - GAO reports on Pay Equity, 1985, 1986
  - GAO reports on Comparable Worth, 1984
  - Comparable Worth: Issues for the `80s (vols. 1 and 2), 1984
  - Pay Equity: An Issue of Race, Ethnicity, and Sex, 1987
  - Manual on Pay Equity, 1980
  - Theoretical articles on Pay Equity
  - Theory: Utopia in America
  - Articles from Women Organizing (eds. Cumming and Schuck), 1979
  - Articles on economics
  - Articles on Sapiro and Hedblom on women and political action
  - Articles/Theory on women in politics
  - Comparable Worth court cases
  - Comparable Worth—CT court cases
  - Report on Pay Equity in Canada
  - Theoretical articles on Women's Studies
  - Copies from Political Culture by Daniel Elezar
  - Theoretical articles on women and labor unions
  - Government publications on women's employment, 1920, 1937, 1941 (Box 4)
  - International Labor Conference reports, 1949, 1975
  - Copies of publications by U.S. Women's Bureau, 1944-1963
  - Comparable Worth theory (articles and notes) 1/3
  - Comparable Worth theory (articles and notes) 2/3
  - Comparable Worth theory (articles and notes) 3/3
  - Articles on iter-government relations
  - Comparable Worth articles
  - Comparable Worth literature and articles
  - Copies from Comparable Worth: Issues and Alternatives, 1980
  - “Women and the Labor Market”, 1981
  - Articles on economic factors in Pay Equity (1/2)
  - Articles on economic factors in Pay Equity (2/2)
  - Articles on Pay Equity for PhDs
  - U.S. Gov't bills on Pay Equity, 1983-1984
  - Comparable Worth and Affirmative Action—articles and notes
  - “Reagan and Affirmative Action”, 1983
  - Job Evaluation literature
  - Pay administration publications
  - Comparable Worth Law Review articles (1/3)
  - Comparable Worth Law Review articles (2/3)
  - Comparable Worth Law Review articles (3/3)
  - Bound Publications, not in folders, including
    - Comparable Worth: The Myth and the Movement, 1984
    - Democratic Theory and the Political Socialization of Physicians (Johansen's dissertation), 1976
    - IPMA Public Personnel Administration— serial issue 16:1 (Sp 1987), 17:3 (Fa 1988), 18:1 (Sp 1989), 1987-1989
    - Review of Public Personnel Administration—serial issue 9:1, 9:2, 1988-1989
    - North Carolina Insight— serial issue 7:2, 1984
    - W.E. Upjohn Publications, 1986-1987
  - “Joint Hearings before the Subcommittees on Human Resources, Civil Service, Compensation and Employee Benefits, etc., Pay Equity: Equal Pay for Work of Equal Value—Parts I and II”
    (two copies of government publications, each with marginal notes by Johansen)
  - Series of index cards containing bibliographic references For Comparable Worth research
  - Set of 18 audio cassette tapes, most are labeled as recordings of various conferences relating to Comparable Worth and Public Administration issues
- Series II: Political Corruption Materials, undated, 1987
  - Assorted articles and clippings on Political Corruption (Box 6)
  - Pages copied from Political Corruption (eds. Heidenheimer, Johnston, Levine), 1987
  - Additional clippings/articles on Political Corruption
  - Early notes and references for Political Corruption bibliography
  - Early references and searches for Political Corruption bib.
  - Political Corruption bibliography searches
    - Political Corruption—
    - correspondence and working notes
    - errata and editing notes
    - working drafts of intro and Chapter 1
    - final drafts, Chapters 2 and 3
    - editing proofs, Chapters 1-3
    - last draft, Chapters 4 and 5
    - editing proofs, Chapters 4-9
    - editing proofs, Chapters 6-10
    - various proof pages
    - proof pages (Folder 2)
    - earlier draft version
    - draft version of index
  - Philosophical literature (Box 7)
    - Chapter 1
  - Theoretical frameworks
    - Chapter 2 (Folder 1 of 2)
    - Chapter 2 (Folder 2 of 2)
  - Political Corruption articles
    - Chapters 1-3 (Folder 1 of 5)
    - Chapters 1-3 (Folder 2 of 5)
    - Chapters 1-3 (Folder 3 of 5)
    - Chapters 1-3 (Folder 4 of 5)
    - Chapters 1-3 (Folder 5 of 5)
  - Court case index for Chapter 3
  - Federal appeals records (Folder 1 of 3)
  - Federal appeals records (Folder 2 of 3)
  - Federal appeals records (Folder 3 of 3)
  - Corruption in elections and public office—Chapter 4
    (draft and clippings)
  - Political Corruption articles
    - Chapter 4 (Folder 1 of 4)
  - Political Corruption articles
    - Chapter 4 (Folder 2 of 4)
    - Chapter 4 (Folder 3 of 4)
    - Chapter 4 (Folder 4 of 4)
  - Business/government corruption—Chapter 5 (Box 8)
  - Public opinion and corruption—Chapter 6
  - Chapter 6 database searches
  - Federal statutes and government documents—Chapter 7
  - Political Corruption articles
    - Chapter 7 (Folder 1 of 2)
    - Chapter 7 (Folder 2 of 2)
  - State and Municipal Corruption—Chapter 8
  - Political Corruption articles—Chapter 8 (Folder 1 of 1)
  - Historical and comparative corruption—Chapter 9
  - Political Corruption articles
    - Chapter 9 (Folder 1 of 3)
    - Chapter 9 (Folder 2 of 3)
    - Chapter 9 (Folder 3 of 3)
  - Bibliographic records—obscure/questionable titles
  - Political Corruption articles
    - Alphabetical (A to B)
    - Alphabetical (C to I)
    - Alphabetical (K to R)
    - Alphabetical (S to Z)
- Series III: Teaching Materials, undated, ca. 1976-1989
  - Chester Barnard materials (Box 9)
  - James Bowman materials
  - Anthony Downs materials
  - Katz and Kahn materials
  - Thoman Kuhn materials
  - James Thompson materials
  - Lecture notes for Public Administration textBooks
  - POLS 361 notes and materials
  - Lecture materials for POLS 361—public organizations, 1987
  - POLS 361 class materials, 1989
  - Student Book reports from POLS 361, 1989
  - Intro to Public Administration materials
  - Class materials for POLS 375-90—Organization and Bureaucracy, 1986
  - Readings for POLS 375—Organization and Bureaucracy
  - Clippings and readings for POLS 375—Organization and Bureaucracy
  - Additional Materials from POLS 375, 1986
  - Materials for POLS 376—analytic tools of public administration
  - POLS 376 materials, ca. 1980
  - PAD 501 materials, ca. 1976
  - PAD 501 materials, ca. 1977
  - Additional lecture notes and Book summaries
  - Additional teaching materials (not sorted)